from that bridge. Some believe that traveling between the two towers will lead you to another dimension -- this bridge has been romanticized as such — that the fall from that frees you from all your worries and grief, and the waters below will cleanse your soul. But let me tell you what actually occurs when the bridge is used as a means of suicide. After a free fall of four to five seconds, the body strikes the water at about 75 miles an hour. That impact shatters bones, some of which then puncture vital organs. Most die on impact. Those that don't generally flail in the water helplessly, and then drown. I don't think that those who contemplate this method of suicide realize how grisly a death that they will face. This is the cord. Except for around the two towers, there is 32 inches of steel paralleling the bridge. This is where most folks stand before taking their lives. I can tell you from experience that once the person is on that cord, and at their darkest time, it is very difficult to bring them back. I took this photo last year as this young woman spoke to an officer contemplating her life. I want to tell you very happily that we were successful that day in getting her back over the rail. When I first began working on the bridge, we had no formal training. You struggled to funnel your way through these calls. This was not only a disservice to those contemplating suicide, but to the officers as well. We've come a long, long way since then. Now, veteran officers and psychologists train new officers. This is Jason Garber. I met Jason on July 22 of last year when I get received a call of a possible suicidal subject sitting on the cord near midspan. I responded, and when I arrived, I observed Jason speaking to a Golden Gate Bridge officer. Jason was just 32 years old and had flown out here from New Jersey. As a matter of fact, he had flown out here on two other occasions from New Jersey to attempt suicide on this bridge. After about an hour of speaking with Jason, he asked us if we knew the story of Pandora's box. Recalling your Greek mythology, Zeus created Pandora, and sent her down to Earth with a box, and told her, "Never, ever open that box." Well one day, curiosity got the better of Pandora, and she did open the box. Out flew plagues, sorrows, and all sorts of evils against man. The only good thing in the box was hope. Jason then asked us, "What happens when you open the box and hope isn't there?" He paused a few moments, leaned to his right, and was gone. This kind, intelligent young man from New Jersey had just committed suicide. I spoke with Jason's parents that evening, and I suppose that, when I was speaking with them, that I didn't sound as if I was doing very well, because that very next day, their family rabbi called to check on me. Jason's parents had asked him to do so. The collateral damage of suicide affects so many people. I pose these questions to you: What would you do if your family member, friend or loved one was suicidal? What would you say? Would you know what to say? In my experience, it's not just the talking that you do, but the listening. Listen to understand. Don't argue, blame, or tell the person you know how they feel, because you probably don't. By just being there, you may just be the turning point that they need. If you think someone is suicidal, don't be afraid to confront them and ask the question. One way of asking them the question is like this: "Others in similar circumstances have thought about ending their life; have you had these thoughts?" Confronting the person head-on may just save their life and be the turning point for them. Some other signs to look for: hopelessness, believing that things are terrible and never going to get better; helplessness, believing that there is nothing that you can do about it; recent social withdrawal; and a loss of interest in life. I came up with this talk just a couple of days ago, and I received an email from a lady that I'd like to read you her letter. She lost her son on January 19 of this year, and she wrote this me this email just a couple of days ago, and it's with her permission and blessing that I read this to you. "Hi, Kevin. I imagine you're at the TED Conference. That must be quite the experience to be there. I'm thinking I should go walk the bridge this weekend. Just wanted to drop you a note. Hope you get the word out to many people and they go home talking about it to their friends who tell their friends, etc. I'm still pretty numb, but noticing more moments of really realizing Mike isn't coming home. Mike was driving from Petaluma to San Francisco to watch the 49ers game with his father on January 19. He never made it there. I called Petaluma police and reported him missing that evening. The next morning, two officers came to my home and reported that Mike's car was down at the bridge. A witness had observed him jumping off the bridge at 1:58 p.m. the previous day. Thanks so much for standing up for those who may be only temporarily too weak to stand for themselves. Who hasn't been low before without suffering from a true mental illness? It shouldn't be so easy to end it. My prayers are with you for your fight. The GGB, Golden Gate Bridge, is supposed to be a passage across our beautiful bay, not a graveyard. Good luck this week. Vicky." I can't imagine the courage it takes for her to go down to that bridge and walk the path that her son took that day, and also the courage just to carry on. I'd like to introduce you to a man I refer to as hope and courage. On March 11 of 2005, I responded to a radio call of a possible suicidal subject on the bridge sidewalk near the north tower. I rode my motorcycle down the sidewalk and observed this man, Kevin Berthia, standing on the sidewalk. When he saw me, he immediately traversed that pedestrian rail, and stood on that small pipe which goes around the tower. For the next hour and a half, I listened as Kevin spoke about his depression and hopelessness. Kevin decided on his own that day to come back over that rail and give life another chance. When Kevin came back over, I congratulated him. "This is a new beginning, a new life." But I asked him, "What was it that made you come back and give hope and life another chance?" And you know what he told me? He said, "You listened. You let me speak, and you just listened." Shortly after this incident, I received a letter from Kevin's mother, and I have that letter with me, and I'd like to read it to you. "Dear Mr. Briggs, Nothing will erase the events of March 11, but you are one of the reasons Kevin is still with us. I truly believe Kevin was crying out for help. He has been diagnosed with a mental illness for which he has been properly medicated. I adopted Kevin when he was only six months old, completely unaware of any hereditary traits, but, thank God, now we know. Kevin is straight, as he says. We truly thank God for you. Sincerely indebted to you, Narvella Berthia." And on the bottom she writes, "P.S. When I visited San Francisco General Hospital that evening, you were listed as the patient. Boy, did I have to straighten that one out." Today, Kevin is a loving father and contributing member of society. He speaks openly about the events that day and his depression in the hopes that his story will inspire others. Suicide is not just something I've encountered on the job. It's personal. My grandfather committed suicide by poisoning. That act, although ending his own pain, robbed me from ever getting to know him. This is what suicide does. For most suicidal folks, or those contemplating suicide, they wouldn't think of hurting another person. They just want their own pain to end. Typically, this is accomplished in just three ways: sleep, drugs or alcohol, or death. In my career, I've responded to and been involved in hundreds of mental illness and suicide calls around the bridge. Of those incidents I've been directly involved with, I've only lost two, but that's two too many. One was Jason. The other was a man I spoke to for about an hour. During that time, he shook my hand on three occasions. On that final handshake, he looked at me, and he said, "Kevin, I'm sorry, but I have to go." And he leapt. Horrible, absolutely horrible. I do want to tell you, though, the vast majority of folks that we do get to contact on that bridge do not commit suicide. Additionally, that very few who have jumped off the bridge and lived and can talk about it, that one to two percent, most of those folks have said that the second that they let go of that rail, they knew that they had made a mistake and they wanted to live. I tell people, the bridge not only connects Marin to San Francisco, but people together also. That connection, or bridge that we make, is something that each and every one of us should strive to do. Suicide is preventable. There is help. There is hope. Thank you very much. (Applause)
desde ese puente. Algunos creen que viajar entre las dos torres los llevará a otra dimensión, este puente se ha idealizado como tal, tal que la caída desde él te libera de todas tus preocupaciones y dolor, y las aguas que pasan debajo limpiarán tu alma. Pero déjenme decirles que sucede cuando el puente se utiliza para cometer suicidio. Después de una caída libre de cuatro a cinco segundos, el cuerpo choca contra el agua aproximadamente a 120 kilómetros por hora. El impacto rompe los huesos, algunos de los cuales perforan órganos vitales. La mayoría muere en el impacto. Los que no, normalmente se azotan en el agua indefensos y luego se ahogan. No creo que los que contemplan este método de suicidio se den cuenta de la macabra muerte a la que se enfrentarán. Este es el cable. Excepto alrededor de las dos torres, hay 32 pulgadas de acero paralelas al puente. Aquí es donde la mayoría de la gente se para antes de quitarse la vida. Puedo decirles por experiencia que una vez que la persona está en ese borde, y en su momento más oscuro, es muy difícil traerlos de vuelta. Tomé esta foto el año pasado mientras esta joven hablaba con un oficial contemplando su vida. Quiero decirles con alegría que tuvimos éxito ese día en traerla de vuelta sobre la barandilla. Cuando empecé a trabajar en el puente, no teníamos ningún entrenamiento formal. Luchábamos para canalizar el camino a través de estas llamadas. Esto no fue sólo un mal servicio a aquellos que contemplan el suicidio, sino a los oficiales también. Hemos recorrido un largo camino desde entonces. Hoy, oficiales veteranos y psicólogos entrenan a los nuevos oficiales. Este es Jason Garber. Lo conocí el 22 de Julio del año pasado al recibir una llamada de un posible sujeto suicida sentado en el cordón cerca del centro. Respondí, y cuando llegué, observé a Jason hablando con un oficial del puente Golden Gate. Jason tenía solo 32 años y había volado hasta aquí desde Nueva Jersey. De hecho, había volado hasta aquí 2 veces antes desde Nueva Jersey para intentar suicidarse desde este puente. Después de cerca de una hora hablando con Jason, nos preguntó si conocíamos la historia de la caja de Pandora. Recordando la mitología griega, Zeus creó a Pandora, y la envió a la Tierra con una caja, y le dijo: "Nunca, nunca abras esa caja". Bueno, un día, la curiosidad pudo más que Pandora, y ella abrió la caja. De ella salieron plagas, penas, y toda clase de males contra el hombre. La única cosa buena en la caja era la esperanza. Entonces Jason nos preguntó, "¿Qué pasa si abres la caja y no hay esperanza?" Se detuvo unos instantes, se inclinó a la derecha, y se fue. Este muchacho amable e inteligente de Nueva Jersey acababa de quitarse la vida. Hablé con los padres de Jason esa noche, y supongo que cuando estaba hablando con ellos, no parecía estar sonando muy bien, porque al día siguiente, el rabino de la familia me llamó para ver cómo estaba. Los padres de Jason se lo habían pedido. Los daños colaterales del suicidio afectan a muchísima gente. Les planteo estas preguntas: ¿Qué harías si un miembro de tu familia, un amigo o alguien amado fuera suicida? ¿Qué dirías? ¿Sabrías qué decir? En mi experiencia, no solamente hay que hablar, sino que hay que escuchar. Escuchar para entender. No discutas, culpes, o le digas a la persona que sabes cómo se siente, porque probablemente no lo sepas. Simplemente estando allí, puedes ser el punto de inflexión que necesitan. Si piensas que alguien es suicida, no tengas miedo de enfrentarlos y hacer la pregunta. Una manera de hacerles la pregunta es: "Otros en similares circunstancias han pensado en acabar su vida; ¿has tenido estos pensamientos?" Confrontar a la persona de frente puede salvarle la vida y ser el punto de inflexión para ellos. Otros signos a buscar: desesperanza, creer que las cosas son terribles y que nunca van a mejorar; Impotencia, creer que no hay nada que puedas hacer al respecto; aislamiento social reciente; y una perdida del interés en la vida. Se me ocurrió esta charla hace apenas un par de días, y recibí un email de una señora y me gustaría leerles su carta. Ella perdió a su hijo el 19 de enero de este año, y me escribió este email hace sólo un par de días, y es con su permiso y bendición que se las leo. "Hola, Kevin. Me imagino que estás en la conferencia TED. Debe ser toda una experiencia estar ahí. Estoy pensando que debería ir a pie al puente este fin de semana. Solo quería dejarte una nota. Espero que puedas contarle a muchas personas y vayan a casa hablando de ello a sus amigos que le cuenten a sus amigos, etc. Todavía estoy bastante insensible, pero notando más momentos de darme cuenta realmente de que Mike no volverá a casa. Mike estaba conduciendo de Petaluma a San Francisco para ver el partido de los 49 con su padre el 19 de enero. Nunca llegó allí. Llamé a la policía de Petaluma y lo reporté como desaparecido esa noche. A la mañana siguiente, dos oficiales vinieron a mi casa y me informaron de que el coche de Mike estaba abajo en el puente. Un testigo lo había visto saltar desde el puente a las 1:58 de la tarde del día anterior. Muchas gracias por luchar por aquellos que puedan estar temporalmente demasiado débiles para luchar por ellos mismos. ¿Quién no ha estado antes mal sin sufrir una verdadera enfermedad mental? No debe ser tan fácil acabar con ella. Mis oraciones están contigo por tu lucha. El GGB, el Puente Golden Gate se supone debe ser un pasaje a través de nuestra hermosa bahía, no un cementerio. Buena suerte esta semana, Vicky". No puedo imaginar el valor que ella necesitó para ir al puente y recorrer el camino que su hijo tomó ese día, y también el valor para salir adelante. Me gustaría presentarles a un hombre al que me refiero con esperanza y valor. El 11 de marzo de 2005, respondí a una llamada de radio por un posible sujeto suicida en la acera del puente cerca de la torre norte. Conduje mi moto por la acera y observé a este hombre, Kevin Berthia, de pie en la acera. Cuando me vio, cruzó de inmediato la barandilla, y se detuvo en ese pequeño tubo que va alrededor de la torre. Durante la hora y media siguiente, escuché como Kevin habló sobre su depresión y desesperanza. Kevin decidió por su cuenta ese día volver sobre ese carril y darle a la vida otra oportunidad. Cuando Kevin volvió, lo felicité. "Este es un nuevo comienzo, una nueva vida". Pero le pregunté, "¿Qué fue lo que hizo que volvieras y le dieras a la esperanza y la vida otra oportunidad?" ¿Y saben lo que me dijo? Dijo: "Me escuchaste. Me dejaste hablar y simplemente escuchaste". Poco después de ese incidente, recibí una carta de la madre de Kevin, y tengo esa carta conmigo, y me gustaría leérselas. "Querido Señor Briggs, Nada borrará los eventos del 11 de marzo, y usted es una de las razones por las que Kevin sigue con nosotros. Sinceramente, creo que Kevin estaba clamando por ayuda. Ha sido diagnosticado con una enfermedad mental para la cual ha sido correctamente medicado. Adopté a Kevin cuando solo tenía seis meses, completamente inconsciente de todos aquellos rasgos hereditarios, pero, gracias a Dios, ahora lo sabemos. Kevin está en orden, como el dice. Le damos gracias a Dios por usted. Sinceramente en deuda con usted, Narvella Berthia". Y al final ella escribe, "P.D. Cuando visité el Hospital General de San Francisco esa noche, usted figuraba como el paciente. "¡Vaya que sí lo tuve que resolver!" Actualmente, Kevin es un padre cariñoso y miembro activo de la sociedad. Habla abiertamente sobre los eventos de ese día y de su depresión con la esperanza de que su historia inspirará a otros. El suicidio no es sólo algo que me he encontrado en el trabajo. Es personal. Mi abuelo se suicidó con veneno. Ese acto, a pesar de terminar su propio dolor, me robo la oportunidad de conocerlo. Esto es lo que hace el suicidio. Para la mayoría de la gente suicida, o aquellos que consideran el suicidio, no pensarían en lastimar a otra persona. Simplemente quieren que su propio dolor acabe. Por lo general, esto se logra solo de tres maneras: dormir, las drogas o el alcohol o la muerte. En mi carrera, he respondido y he estado involucrado en cientos de enfermedades mentales y llamadas de suicidio alrededor del puente. De esos incidentes en los que he estado directamente involucrado, solo he perdido dos, pero esos dos son demasiado. Uno fue Jason. El otro fue un hombre al que le hablé cerca de una hora. Durante ese tiempo, me estrechó la mano en tres ocasiones. En el apretón final, me miró, y me dijo, "Kevin, lo siento, pero me tengo que ir". Y saltó. Horrible, absolutamente horrible. Yo quiero decirles, sin embargo, que la gran mayoría de la gente que nosotros llegamos a contactar en ese puente no se suicidan. Además, esos pocos que han saltado del puente y vivido y que pueden hablar de ello, ese 1% o 2%, la mayoría de esas personas han dicho que al segundo que dejan de lado la barandilla se dieron cuenta de que habían cometido un error y querían vivir. Yo le digo a la gente, el puente no sólo conecta Marin con San Francisco, sino también a la gente. Esa conexión, o puente que hacemos, es algo que todos y cada uno de nosotros debemos esforzarnos por hacer. El suicidio se puede prevenir. Hay ayuda. Hay esperanza. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)